Austin Coursey

Summary _

3rd year computer science Ph.D. student at Vanderbilt University. Interested in developing and applying machine learning solutions to solve problems in real-world complex systems. Research interests include reinforcement learning, prognostics, anomaly detection, and continual learning. Recently completed a NASA System-Wide Safety project where I developed and deployd a controller that improved unmanned aerial vehicle control under strong wind disturbances. Currently researching the intersection of safe and continual reinforcement learning as part of my NSF Graduate Research Fellowship.

Education ____

PhD Vanderbilt University, Computer Science

 Member of the Modeling and Analysis of Complex Systems (MACS) lab under Professor Gautam Biswas at the Institute for Software Integrated Systems. Nashville, TN Aug 2022 – present

BS Murray State University, Computer Science and Mathematics

- Undergraduate Thesis Data-driven Models for Remaining Useful Life Estimation of Aircraft Engines and Hard Disk Drives
- 4.0 GPA
- · Honors Degree and Summa Cum Laude
- Outstanding Senior in Computer Science x2 and Mathematics
- Multiple leadership positions include President of Association for Computing Machinery and Vice President of Association of Information Technology Professionals

Murray, KY Aug 2018 – May 2022

Experience _____

Vanderbilt University, NSF Graduate Research Fellow

• Researching the intersection of safe and continual reinforcement learning. Funded by National Science Foundation.

Nashville, TN Aug 2024 – present

Vanderbilt University, Graduate Research Assistant

Graduate RA in the Modeling and Analysis of Complex Systems lab in the Institute for Software Integrated Systems at Vanderbilt University. Worked at a NASA-funded unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) system-wide safety project. Developed a reinforcement learning controller to counteract wind and fault disturbances to maintain safety.

Nashville, TN Jan 2023 – Aug 2024

Vanderbilt University, Graduate Teaching Assistant

Graduate TA for five sections of Vanderbilt University's CS 2212 (Discrete Structures) course. Held office hours for dozens of students, graded homework and exams, and assisted professors with various tasks such as running class for the day.

Nashville, TN Aug 2022 – Dec 2022

Carnegie Mellon University, Undergraduate Researcher

Summer researcher at Carnegie Mellon University's Research Experience for Undergraduates in Software Engineering (REUSE) program. Evaluated the quality of machine learning model documentation in the form of model cards, a standard proposed by Google. Designed a study to determine the effectiveness of a novel

Pittsburgh, PA June 2021 – Aug 2021 tool that autogenerates model cards for Jupyter Notebooks. Presented findings at a poster session at the end of the summer. Paper published in CHI.

 United Systems and Software, Software Development Intern Performed full-stack website development using Angular (TypeScript, CSS, and HTML), C#.NET, and SQL. Developed a web portal for utility customers across Kentucky and some surrounding states to pay their bills and participated in Agile, team-based development. 	Benton, KY ne 2020 – June 2021
 Land Between the Lakes National Recreation Area, Webmaster Intern Developed and maintained a website with over 129,000 monthly page visits. Created over 50 individual web pages using WordPress, HTML, and CSS. 	Golden Pond, KY Aug 2019 – Aug 2022
Awards and Honors	
National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellow	2024
Best Reviewer Award - KDD 2024	2024
Murray State University Outstanding Senior Computer Science Senior (x2)	2021-2022
Murray State University Outstanding Mathematics Senior	2022
Publications	
FT-AED: Benchmark Dataset for Early Freeway Traffic Anomalous Event Detection Austin Coursey, Junyi Ji, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, William Barbour, Yuhang Zhang, Tyler Derr, Gautam Biswas, Daniel B Work	Dec 2024
10.48550/arXiv.2406.15283 ☑ (Neural Information Processing Systems - NeurIPS 2024 Datasets and Benchmarks)	
Quantifying the Sim-To-Real Gap in UAV Disturbance Rejection Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas	Oct 2024
10.4230/OASIcs.DX.2024.16 ☑ (International Conference on Principles of Diagnosis and Resilient Systems - DX 2024)	
Data-Driven RUL Prediction Using Performance Metrics	Oct 2024
Abel Diaz-Gonzalez, Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Chetan S. Kulkarni, Gautam Biswas	
10.4230/OASIcs.DX.2024.21 ☑ (International Conference on Principles of Diagnosis and Resilient Systems - DX 2024)	
An Experimental Framework for Evaluating the Safety and Robustness of UAV Controllers	Aug 2024
Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas 10.2514/6.2024-4548 ☑ (AIAA Aviation Forum 2024)	
Hybrid control framework of uavs under varying wind and payload conditions Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas 10.23919/ACC60939.2024.10645000 ☑ (American Control Conference - ACC 2024)	July 2024
Determining the temporal factors of survival associated with brain and nervous system cancer patients: A hybrid machine learning methodology	July 2024
Gopal Nath, Austin Coursey, Joseph Ekong, Elham Rastegari, Saptarshi Sengupta, Asli Z Dag, Dursun Delen	
10.1080/20479700.2023.2196101 ☑ (International Journal of Healthcare Management)	
R Code Authorship Attribution using the ASAP Tool	July 2024

Austin Coursey, Matthew Tennyson, Vlad Krotov	
10.17705/3jmwa.000090 ☑ (Journal of the Midwest Association for Information Systems)	
Time-Series Few Shot Anomaly Detection for HVAC Systems	June 2024
Yuxin Huang, Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas	
10.1016/j.ifacol.2024.07.255 ☑ (IFAC Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety for Technical Processes - Safe Process 2024)	
Comparison of Transfer Learning Techniques for Building Energy Forecasting	June 2024
Shansita Das Sharma, Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas	
10.1016/j.ifacol.2024.07.214 ☑ (IFAC Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety for Technical Processes - Safe Process 2024)	
A Flexible Data-Driven Prognostics Model Using System Performance Metrics	June 2024
Abel Diaz-Gonzalez, Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas	
10.1016/j.ifacol.2024.07.221 ☑ (IFAC Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety for Technical Processes - Safe Process 2024)	
An interactive web-based tool for predicting and exploring brain cancer survivability	Nov 2023
Gopal Nath, Austin Coursey, Yang Li, Srikanth Prabhu, Harish Garg, Shaymal C Halder, Saptarshi Sengupta	
10.1016/j.health.2022.100132 🗹 (Healthcare Analytics)	
Enhancing Prognostics with Self-Supervised Imputation	Sept 2023
Austin Coursey, Abel Diaz-Gonzalez, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas	•
International Workshop on Principles of Diagnosis - DX'23 - Workshop Paper	
On Learning Data-Driven Models For In-Flight Drone Battery Discharge Estimation From Real Data	June 2023
Austin Coursey, Marcos Quinones-Grueiro, Gautam Biswas	
10.1109/SMARTCOMP58114.2023.00038 ☑ (IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing - SMARTCOMP 2023)	
Large-scale End-of-Life Prediction of Hard Disks in Distributed Datacenters	June 2023
Rohan Mohapatra, Austin Coursey, Saptarshi Sengupta	
10.1109/SMARTCOMP58114.2023.00069 ☑ (IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing - SMARTCOMP 2023 - Workshop Paper)	
Aspirations and practice of ml model documentation: Moving the needle with nudging and traceability	Apr 2023
Avinash Bhat, Austin Coursey (joint primary), Grace Hu, Sixian Li, Nadia Nahar, Shurui Zhou, Christian Kästner, Jin LC Guo	
10.1145/3544548.3581518 ☑ (CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems - CHI 2023)	
Incorporating a machine learning model into a Web-based administrative decision support tool for predicting workplace absenteeism	June 2022
Gopal Nath, Yawei Wang, Austin Coursey, Krishna K Saha, Srikanth Prabhu, Saptarshi Sengupta	
10.3390/info13070320 🗹 (Information)	
Remaining useful life estimation of hard disk drives using bidirectional lstm net- works	Dec 2021
Austin Coursey, Gopal Nath, Srikanth Prabhu, Saptarshi Sengupta	

10.1109/BigData52589.2021.9671605 ☑ (IEEE International Conference on Big Data - Big Data 2024)

Theses _

Data-driven models for remaining useful life estimation of aircraft engines and hard disk drives

May 2022

Austin Coursey

digitalcommons.murraystate.edu/honorstheses/116 🗹

Conferences and Refereeing

AIAA Aviation Forum July 2024

• System-Wide Safety session Co-Chair.

IEEE Conference on Smart Computing

June 2023

· Student volunteer.

Refereeing

- International Workshop on Principles of Diagnosis (DX 2024)
- Journal of Aerospace Information Systems (JAIS)
- IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics
- ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD 2024) Best Reviewer Award
- IFAC Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety for Technical Processes (Safe Process 2024)
- American Control Conference (ACC 2023, 2024)
- Expert Systems with Applications